[Music]
you had a really interesting wonderful
conversation with jordan peterson
earlier this year and a lot of people
like the read the comments and a lot of
people thought it was one of his best
conversations seem that you really
sparked off each other and yes i enjoyed
it yeah yeah can you talk more about
that he came from the now-famous
interview with Kathy Newman on channel 4
so he was quite you know wired he
arrived extremely late and he had half
an hour between them and getting to
Paris we had had we'd never met one
another and I knew actually very little
about Jordan Peterson has written work
he knew pretty little about mine and we
were just told sit down and shoot and we
had no idea where we were going so he
just started talking
so why the maestro's emissary and he
just went from there but what I felt was
here was you know a super intelligent
man who had wide-ranging interests in
psychology philosophy and didn't rule
out a spiritual angle to things and I
don't think that I would and in the film
I in that clip I think he probably comes
out that there are aspects of what
Jordan was saying that I was getting
well yes but so I didn't entirely kind
of not a Peter Peter Sohn Ian but I do
have a huge respect for him and we had a
great conversation and we were proposing
to do more yeah I mean one of the most
common comments was where's the rest of
this interview well actually I just
he's been fabulously busy in the last
year and I had to email him about
something else actually just yesterday
and he wrote back saying and top of my
list for when I begin again doing a
podcast in the new year is to do one
with you listening to it that was very
interesting especially as you hadn't you
weren't that aware of each other's work
how it seemed that your theories mapped
onto something he talks about a lot
which is the balance of ordering chaos
and the known versus the unknown is that
a right-brain left-brain for
no is there a parallel not much there is
a bit
I mean Festival I'm sorry I don't accept
his order is mail than chaos is female I
don't even understand that and I do
accept that the left hemisphere which is
nor what he's talking about is concerned
above all with consistency so and that's
why it over relies on systems procedures
algorithms that produce results are
consistent with everything else it knows
the right hemisphere is open to
everything as you were without prejudice
and it therefore sees that there are
many things that actually don't then do
that now in the left hemisphere those
just get ruled out and I think that's
where we wraps intellectually we have a
system that is self-consistent a cake
flan getting rolled out and everybody
can't see well not everybody but many
people cannot see a way out of this
because because actually once you're
inside this hall of mirrors as I call it
you can't see the chinks where you can
sort of get out what I think Jordan
Peterson is doing is he has enormous
rhetorical strength and he's really you
know allowing people to to see that
there are things that is not that are
not included this model and I'm hoping
that I enter perhaps in a different way
I'm doing the same thing if you like I
did say to him you've seemed very keen
on order which might exclude chaos but
chaos is like the sort of grit in the
oyster shell there is a need for this
resistance this is a theme that is very
important in the book I'm now writing
which is that nothing comes into being
or can be without resistance and some
simple way of thinking about it is that
actually we can't move if it were not
for friction friction is actually
stopping you moving actually moving
dependence on friction a more
sophisticated one is to do with the
nature of flow which is the overarching
merciful' of flow as what it is what the
universe is you know Heraclitus is
saying everything flows this is
brilliant
you didn't say everything changes he
said everything flows which is a
different matter but anyway flow
produces something very important it
produces irregularities and it only
actually exists if there is a degree of
containment so if water if if there is
no containment water is still and does
nothing it's the containment that causes
the flow and it's obstructions to the
flow that caused turbulence and
turbulence is massively created or flow
in nature is turbulent or at least
almost all that flowing in nature is
turbulent and turbulence is one of the
last things that we can map we know how
we we're getting to grip we don't really
know but we're getting to grips better
with quantum mechanics than we are with
the the mathematical equations for flow
they're so complex and this they're
almost infinitely complex that it is
said that we can never actually do it so
they might be an instance of a kind of
chaos that is vastly created partly
because it's the coming together of
order with disorder and I'm always
saying we need division and we need
Union it's not just that union is
marvelous all as one and that's the
perfectly why's point of view it's not
that everything is separate and distinct
and atomistic we need to bring these two
apparently opposite points of view
together we need Union and division but
we need at a meta level the union of
them not the division of them which is
what we now have so that is imaged in
this business of water and let me just
give you a
something that might strike viewers if
you take an entirely straight sided pipe
and you put waters run water through it
at such a speed that it can run smoothly
and you then place at right angles
perpendicular to the flow an entirely
straight metal bar that doesn't block
the flow what you get what do you think
you get you get something imaginable
that is both orderly and beautiful and
nothing like the rector linearity of it
you get something called Carmen Street
vortex which is a series of interlocking
flows that have clear structure that are
also unwrapped Abul and and endlessly
variable so out of this unpromising
conjunction a rectilinear unitary things
comes this multifarious creative beauty
that is I think it a lovely image for me
so I remember in the interview you asked
you asked that question about that he
was a little bit more suspicious of Kaos
than the newer and his answer was that
he thought it was right to put yourself
on the right border between order and
chaos yes
which is where we came together yes and
he acknowledged that there needs to be
this this coming together of order and
chaos
so I don't think we're apart on this it
was just the difference of emphasis
because whatever else it seemed from
what he'd just been saying in the
conversation that he I mean after all
famously he said get your room in order
which I'm in favor of I'm also in favor
of a slight element of disorder in the
order and indeed the the art of beauty
is a uniting water with disorder pattern
with things that can't be mapped and
what do you make of the sort of the
criticisms cuz often he's described as a
fraud or a charlatan in some of the the
media coverage but when you watch the
interview with yourself I mean that's
that's a very high level conversation
the idea of him as a
a charlatan just seems kind of bizarre
it's it's outrageous
it's it's disrespectful its dismissive
and it's entirely typical of blinkered
liberalism he you can disagree with him
about many things and I would disagree
with him about a number of things but to
say that is just to show how pink and
you are he's clearly an extraordinary
man and I mean I think what strikes
people is that he was relatively unknown
and then he became known but that's what
life isn't it disapproval Rochelle's
yeah maybe some jealousy but I mean what
what's interesting for me is someone who
I went out to interview him in October
last year and as soon as yeah before
well before the Kathy Newman interview
yeah and my immediate as soon as I saw a
couple of his lectures I thought this is
of this is the important piece that
we're missing in our culture right now
so none of like his his his meteoric
success since then has been no surprise
to me because I thought it's not to me
and also I find it very interesting that
in this very new atheist kind of
dominated world
yeah something we have a man talking
about religious experience and spiritual
experience one of the most famous
academics in the world
how significant do you think that as I
think it is very significant I myself
probably prefer more you might call it
mystical approach to religion then then
Jordan and although I wouldn't want to
you know narrow down I don't know him
and his views well enough to but I
sensed that I the things that really
interest me in the spiritual tradition
Taoism Zen Sufism
the medieval mystics meister eckhart the
author of the Cloud of Unknowing you
know Jakob Irma Udo that score and these
people seem to me to be expressing very
profound truths and indeed in that talk
with Jordan I brought up the lurianic
kabbalah which is something I came to
only about four or five years ago but
which is seems to me absolutely packed
with with the most vivid insights in
into the nature of things which which
illuminates um the the right left
hemisphere thing that I've been talking
about I just couldn't believe it that it
there it was in 1600 and something
people insures it this you see this is
the thing I think people have an
intuitive knowledge that them their mind
is actually not unitary that there are
different aspects to it that have
differently valid ways of thinking but
that the culture forces you to response
one point of view one of the values of
having a religious culture is that it
allows you to espouse what first of all
it instills humility which is no bad
thing it seems to me simply a failure of
intellect to believe your intellect is
so powerful that it knows everything or
even could and so no doubt in evolution
is an ongoing process we let I mean a
mouse by thinking those everything but
whatever it comes after us may look back
on us and think with their poor little
brains so the Harrigan's
of we can understand it all is
breathtaking so one thing good thing
about religion is it instills a sense of
you know limits and humility which I
think are very good it embodies
I mean this is old old hat but it
embodies certain kinds of moral
principle which of course it's not
necessary to an atheist can be a very
moral person but it's actually quite
useful in the culture to have norms
against which to judge things at the
moment the norms those of me and what I
need and so on which are not so good is
we should simply trade it down you refer
to it just then about the the idea of
the left brain as a Hall of Mirrors yes
and I think this is in your RSA
animation as well the idea that the
things I think I paraphrase but
something like the things that might
lead us out yeah are immediately seized
upon I think what you're talking about
is any kind of experience beyond the
left brain is immediately seized upon by
the left brain and brought back into
could could you describe that because I
also sounds a lot like the definition of
post-modernism which is that it is that
it takes the surface and strips out the
meaning and then you're back years even
the transcendental is then taken and
deconstructed and you're absolutely
right and the there are good things in
post-modernism but there are also
problems with it when it claims that
because truth is complex evolving
difficult to pin down there is no truth
I mean once we're in that realm you know
you can't even have a conversation
because it depends on some kinds of
truth I couldn't get out of bed without
it so that's my problem with it although
you know one of the things I disagree
with about Jordan does he dismisses the
whole thing of face model is where
there's rather valuable strands do
however you your question was not really
about post-modernism per se it was about
this Hall of Mirrors
and I think that what happens is the
left hemisphere is quite good on
indignant it and that might sound like
you
you're being very metaphorical but but I
you know I have nothing a good metal
fist they all have you understand things
but it's also literally true
neuropsychiatric lee the people who have
right hemisphere damage in such colossal
denial sometimes that it beggars belief
you know and you know I've talked about
this before good perhaps I'll just say
it again because it's an illustration
that that brings it home somebody can
have a completely paralyzed part of
their body that the left arm after a
right hemisphere is straight and they
will absolutely deny there's anything
wrong with it and when asked to move it
they will go there without moving it and
they they're convinced and if you bring
it round in front of them and say now
don't move that they will say oh that's
not my arm that belongs to the bloke in
so it's that bad and people you know
with right hemisphere now if they have
no clue of what it is that's wrong with
them so they get very angry and
challenged when people say actually
there's a problem here
irritability and anger are very strong
in the left hemisphere and I think that
that I think what I was getting at in
the Hall of Mirrors is several things
really I mean one is the the self
referential nature of the structure of
the systemic thinking which is not open
to new information but also that the the
things that used to speak to us about
something beyond if you like to say our
normal everyday idea about the world
where the natural world art religion
cultural wisdom handed down from
generation to generation
spirituality these things and that each
of them we've either become alienated
from in some way were the ones that we
haven't have been ionized and mocked and
dismissed and a point I make in the book
is incidental but in de it is
interesting the the left hemisphere
never subtle tends to piss on things it
doesn't understand and when the
Communists
revolution happened in Russia the
churches were actually she sounded
public lavatories in some cases and then
of course you've got Marcel Duchamp
literally turning art into the paper I
know and you've got in the 20th century
loads and loads of people whose artwork
was feces so there's something
incredibly unsubtle imaginatively but
it's really like a gesture you and
that is the level of converse one can
have with the left hemisphere and
sometimes I feel that it's the level of
Congress that one can have with not the
brighter ones but the less bright New
Atheists
the internet is full of atheistic trolls
scientistic believers that they know it
all and everything else is rubbish
and this is very sad you spoke before
about it was interesting when you
mentioned Taoism because that was sort
of implicit in a lot of what you were
saying before when you were talking
about the union of opposites and how the
the idea in Taoism is that things that
seem like they're opposites are actually
two parts of a composite whole and I
think in the Jordan Pederson in 2b you
also talked about how that's the
Hegelian perspective as well that there
is a greater synthesis that that
incorporates two things that are seen as
and can you talk a bit about Taoism and
how that maps onto what your to your yes
your view your work I'm not the only
person to have read in their early
twenties Alan Watts his doubt of the
watercourse way and that was an
eye-opening experience for me because
again I thought oh gosh the this
resonates enormously was my experience
of the world and yet it's not what I was
taught at at school and actually left
you know it's interesting that and
that the contemporary view by a
reduction this is that and you wouldn't
believe any of these weird thinking us
if they if you hadn't been indoctrinated
in them but in fact my indoctrination
was very much in the rationalist
tradition but I left school believing
certain things that since then I found
arguments and sophisticated philosophers
and evidence in science that they may
well be true but I couldn't have known
that at that stage and they were that
the parts are not the same as the whole
the sum of the parts simply is not
whatever you say the same as the whole
if you say well what is that what is
this mystery thing that's been added in
but that's of course because you're
already starting from the wrong point of
view so the fact of the relationship of
parts for how the idea that the world is
a responsive thing that experience
responds to you and you respond to it
it's not a one-way process you know many
others of these things that the
embodiment of ideas is as important as
you know the context changes of them
that making things implicit suddenly
changes it into something else
so all those ideas I intuitively
espoused and then I came across Taoism
which says things like the Dow that can
be named is not in fact that's the start
of the data chain the the Dow that can
be named is not the real Dow which is
how exactly what I had been in queue
thing that once you've pinned it down
and named it there's no longer the same
thing and actually that is also there in
the Christian tradition for example
central Gaston said if you understand it
is not God you understand so all of that
spoke to me but also what spoke to me
was this idea of flow and movement which
I had come across because Eric lysis was
legitimate in Heraclitus who I still
think is probably the most important
philosopher who ever lived even though
we only have fragments of what he
thought but his thoughts are so resonant
and so penetrating that I keep coming
back to them so the idea of flow of
that's in the watercourse way that's in
the now is also in the site of
Heraclitus it's also there
in Chinese and Japanese poetry that
things are like a river on which
whirlpools and vortices appear and then
disappear into the flow and image I like
very much which the German philosopher
shelling took up which is that it's a
good image for me of how we relate to
the stream of life as a whole that for a
while there are worlds or vortices
caused by resistance and they are there
and they're photographed although
they're measurable they are material but
they are not separate from the flow of
the water because they are the flow and
they also come out of it and go back
into it so there's no need to find a way
in which this individual entity is made
to care here with the whole so this
Minear of the movement of water is you
know I can't get into all of it but that
that runs through my book and it's a
taoist idea it's a Heric like an idea
and part of the the sense some of the
interviews that we've done have been
about the idea that there are thinkers
and there are perspectives that have
been left out of the sort of mainstream
tradition and are really important to
recapture I think Taoism Alan Watts is a
really good one already but who are the
key thinkers that you think are really
essential for us to kind of reintegrate
into our into our knowledge Western ones
yes yes well what stands out for me is
William James and only their song the
beginning of the century of a song was
the most famous philosopher in the world
and he's credited with causing the first
traffic jam on Broadway because so many
people wanted to come in the a.m speak
and curiously he's been sidelined since
about the thirties and forties he's been
recently rediscovered because he said
things in the 1870s there's a very
recently being confirmed
by quantum mechanics and quantum field
theory so that is interesting
he understood the nature on the
importance of time and motion which play
a big part in the last part of the book
I'm currently working on and that might
sound rather limited but actually what
he shows you is that a whole different
view of what we are what the cosmos is
and how we relate to it comes from
re-imagining in fact getting in touch
once again with the reality of time and
the reality of motion I think one of the
things we the biggest mistakes we make
is to say we'll react that time is just
a real oriya fantasy it's just a sort of
a delusion and actually when we break
out of whatever it is aware now we'll
see that time is it's not existent it's
quite possible that in a world we cannot
even conceive of course then things that
we cannot conceive by definition might
occur within the through everything we
know about the cosmos time is
fundamental and cannot be just so and it
may sound as I say a rather limited
thing but in believe me Bell Tolls
philosophy is extraordinarily redolent
and I read a few years ago something
called creative evolution revolucion
Claire trees which is translated now and
it is his introduction to metaphysics
and a series of other pieces which if
people want to approach but some of that
is the place to start and it's very rare
for me now to read a book and be so
electrified that I can't put it down and
I'm marking all the way down the page
but with this I was so I think he is
very important I think William James is
so central to much thought that has been
left behind again from the same period
before a kind of material upsetting in
the interwar period there were many
steps backwards you know we made huge
steps forwards in biology very
sophisticated thinkers but between the
wars a new mechanism came forth in
biology when I started writing about
science in this book I thought well
physics and to a degree chemistry very
much on my side in terms of a philosophy
of how things are it's not atomistic is
not mechanical etc and then I discovered
that actually this is being set down by
biologists once again but the last time
it was said was really up until the 30s
and 40s and then there was a dark age in
which everything was likened and and we
were very excited by this wonderful
discovery about DNA in the you know it's
all like code in the computer and so on
well I can't even begin we'd have to do
another talk about that because I could
talk for now about why organisms are not
mechanisms it is quite true that if you
want to look at a tiny detail like
what's going on on this side of a
membrane and the other you can see a
kind of mechanism in other words a chain
of causation but it simply doesn't apply
to the organism as a whole
it cannot be native not because we don't
know enough but intrinsically it is not
the right way to think about it and if
you doubt that then I would that is one
thing I explained early on in the new
rule and here I might say there is a
very good book called everything flows
which is a book of essays by
philosophers biologists chemists
physicists edited by Duprey and
published by a rupee which came out in
May this year which is very very
interesting
[Music]
you